You've heard of your I.Q., your general intelligence,
지능지수라는 말 들어보셨을 겁니다. 여러분의 지성을 일컫는 말이죠.
but what's your Psy-Q?
그런데 심리지수란 건 뭘까요?
How much do you know about what makes you tick,
사람들이 특정한 식으로 행동하는이유에 대해 여러분은 얼마나 알고 계시나요?
and how good are you at predicting other people's behavior
또 타인이나 심지어 여러분의 행동을 예측하는 일은 얼마나 잘하시나요?
And how much of what you think you know about psychology is wrong?
또, 심리학에 대해 갖춘 지식 중에서 어느 정도나 잘못된 것일까요?
Let's find out by counting down the top 10 myths of psychology.
심리학에 관한 열가지 신화를 통해 잘못된 것들을 알아보도록 하죠.
You've probably heard it said that when it comes to their psychology,
여러분은 한번 쯤 들어보셨을 법한 것은 자신들의 심리학에 대해 고려할 때,
it's almost as if men are from Mars and women are from Venus.
거의 항상 남자는 화성에서 왔고, 여자는 금성에서 온 것같다고 합니다.
But how different are men and women really?
하지만 실제로 남자와 여자는 얼마나 다른 걸까요?
To find out, let's start by looking at something
이를 알아보기 위해, 일단 남녀 사이에 확실하게 차이나는 것을 살펴보고
and plotting some psychological gender differences on the same scale.
심리학적인 성별간의 차이점을 동일한 척도상에서 대비해 보도록 하겠습니다.
One thing men and women do really differ on
남자와 여자간에 실제로 차이나는 능력 중 하나는
is how far they can throw a ball.
그들이 공을 얼마나 멀리 던질 수 있느냐 하는 것입니다.
So if we look at the data for men here,
여기 남자들의 데이타를 보시면,
we see what is called a normal distribution curve.
정상 분포 곡선이라는 걸 볼 수 있습니다.
A few men can throw a ball really far, and a few men not far at all,
남자들 소수는 정말 멀리 던지고, 남자들 소수는 멀리 던지지 못하지만,
but most a kind of average distance.
남자들 대부분은 평균적인 거리를 던졌습니다.
And women share the same distribution as well,
여자들도 역시 비슷한 분포 상태를 보입니다만
but actually there's quite a big difference.
사실 남녀 사이엔 커다란 차이가 있습니다.
In fact, the average man can throw a ball further
사실, 평균 수준의 남자라면 모든 여성 중 대략 98% 보다
than about 98 percent of all women.
더 멀리 던질 수 있거든요.
So now let's look at what some psychological gender differences
이와 동일하게 표준화된 척도상에서
look like on the same standardized scale.
심리학에서 말하는 성별간의 차이를 살펴 봅시다.
Any psychologist will tell you
심리학자라는 여러분에게 말하길
that men are better at spatial awareness than women --
남자들의 공간지각능력이 여자들보다 뛰어나다고 할 겁니다.
so things like map-reading, for example -- and it's true,
예를들어, 지도 읽는 능력 같은 건데, 맞는 말입니다.
but let's have a look at the size of this difference.
하지만 그 차이의 정도를 살펴봅시다.
It's tiny; the lines are so close together they almost overlap.
아주 작죠. 두 선이 너무 근접해서 거의 겹칠 정도입니다.
In fact, the average woman is better than 33 percent of all men,
사실, 평균 수준의 여성은 모든 남성 중 33%보다 낫습니다.
and of course, if that was 50 percent,
물론 그게 남정의 50%보다 나았다면,
then the two genders would be exactly equal.
두 성별의 능력은 정확히 동등했겠죠.
It's worth bearing in mind that this difference and the next one I'll show you
기억하시면 좋을것은, 다음으로 보시게 될 이러한 차이는
are pretty much the biggest psychological gender differences
현재까지 심리학 분야에서 남녀 간의 심리적 차이점이라 발견된 것 중에서
ever discovered in psychology.
가장 큰 것이라 말할 수 있습니다.
So here's the next one.
자, 그 다음것이 여기 있습니다.
Any psychologist will tell you that women are better
심리학자는 모두 언어와 문법적 능력에서 여성이 남성보다 뛰어나다고 말할 겁니다.
So here's performance on the standardized grammar test.
자, 표준화된 문법시험에서 나타난 수행평가 결과를 보시죠.
There go the women. There go the men.
이것이 여자들 거고 이것이 남자들 겁니다.
Again, yes, women are better on average, but the lines are so close
다시 말해, 그렇죠. 평군적으로는 여자들이 낫지만 두 선은 매우 가까워
that 33 percent of men are better than the average woman,
남성들 중의 33%가 평균치의 여성들보다 더 낫습니다.
and again, if it was 50 percent,
다시 말해, 만일 그 비율 50%였다면 남녀간의 능력 차이는 전혀 없는 거죠.
So it's not really a case of Mars and Venus.
그러니 실상은 화성과 금성처럼 다른 사례는 아닙니다.
It's more a case of, if anything, Mars and Snickers:
마스와 스니커즈 사이의 차이정도죠: (마스/스니커즈 : 쵸코렛바 이름)
basically the same, but one's maybe slightly nuttier than the other.
근본적으로는 똑같은 건데, 한쪽에 어쩌면 견과류 양이 더 많은거죠.
I won't say which.
어느 쪽이 더 많은지는 말하지 않겠어요.
Now we've got you warmed up.
자 이제 워밍업이 되셨을테니,
Let's psychoanalyze you using the famous Rorschach inkblot test.
유명한 로르샤흐의 잉크반점 검사법으로 여러분들 심리분석을 해 봅시다.
So you can probably see two, I dunno, two bears or two people or something.
보시기에 곰 두마리, 두 사람, 또는 다른 것으로 보이실 수도 있습니다.
But what do you think they're doing?
그런데, 그것들이 뭘 하고 있다고 생각하시나요?
Put your hand up if you think they're saying hello.
그들이 인사하고 있다고 생각하시는 분은 손을 들어 보세요.
Not many people. Okay.
그리 많지 않군요. 좋습니다.
Put your hands up if you think they are high-fiving.
그들이 하이 파이브를 한다고 생각하시면 손을 들어 보세요.
Okay. What if you think they're fighting?
알겠습니다. 혹시 그들이 싸우는거라 생각하시는 분?
Only a few people there.
아주 소수군요.
Okay, so if you think they're saying hello or high-fiving,
그들이 인사를 한다거나, 하이 파이브를 하는 거라 생각하셨다면,
then that means you're a friendly person.
그건 여러분들이 친철한 성격의 소유자란 의미입니다.
If you think they're fighting,
그들이 싸우고 있는 거라 생각하셨던
you're a bit more of a nasty, aggressive person.
그런 분들은 호전적인 성격에 조금 더 가깝다고 할 수 있겠죠.
Are you a lover or a fighter, basically.
기본적으로 사랑스런 사람인가요, 호전적인 사람인가요?
What about this one?
이건 어떻습니까?
This isn't really a voting one, so on three everyone shout out what you see.
이건 손을 들만한 그림이 아니므로 셋을 세면 생각하신 바를 외쳐주세요.
One, two, three. (Audience shouting)
하나, 둘, 셋 (청중들 외침)
I heard hamster. Who said hamster?
햄스터라고 하는 걸 들었는데, 누가 햄스터라고 하셨죠?
That was very worrying.
걱정되게 히는 것이었는데요.
A guy there said hamster.
저 쪽 남성분이 햄스터라고 하셨군요
Well, you should see some kind of two-legged animal here,
여러분은 여기에 두 다리를 가진 동물을 보셨을테고
and then the mirror image of them there.
그것을 맞은 편의 거울 이미지로 보셨을 겁니다
If you didn't, then this means that you have difficulty
여러분이 그렇지 않으셨다면, 이건 여러가지 일이 동시에 벌어지는 상황을
Except, of course, it doesn't mean that at all.
단, 물론, 그것은 그걸 의미하는 게 전혀 아닙니다.
Rorschach inkblot tests have basically no validity
로르샤흐의 잉크반점 검사는 사실 사람들의 인성 진단을 하는 데
when it comes to diagnosing people's personality
실효성이 전혀 없는 것으로
and are not used by modern-day psychologists.
현대 심리학에서는 사용되지 않습니다.
In fact, one recent study found that when you do try
사실 최근 한 연구를 통해 밝혀진 바에 따르면
schizophrenia was diagnosed
완벽하게 정상인인 잠가자들 중 정신 분열이라 오진된 사례가
So if you didn't do that well on this,
따라서 만일 이 검사를 잘 치러내지 못하신 분들은
maybe you are not a very visual type of person.
그냥 시각적인 사람이 아니라고 생각하시면 될 겁니다.
So let's do another quick quiz to find out.
자, 또 다른 간단한 퀴즈를 해서 알아보도록 합시다.
When making a cake, do you prefer to -- so hands up for each one again --
케잌을 만드실 때 어느 쪽을 선호하시는지 다시 손을 들어 주세요
do you prefer to use a recipe book with pictures?
그림이 있는 요리책을 선호하십니까?
Yeah, a few people.
네, 몇 분 계시네요.
Have a friend talk you through?
친구가 옆에서 차례대로 말해주는 게 좋으신 분?
Or have a go, making it up as you go along?
무턱대고 해보고, 점차적으로 만들어가며 해결하시는 분?
Quite a few people there.
꽤 계시네요.
Okay, so if you said A,
좋습니다, 만약 A를 선택하셨다면
then this means that you are a visual learner
시각에 의존한 학습자란 뜻입니다.
and you learn best when information is presented in a visual style.
정보가 시각적 형태로 제시될 때 가장 잘 배우시는 분이라는 뜻입니다.
If you said B, it means you're an auditory learner,
만일 B 라고 하셨다면, 청각에 의존한 학습자이신 겁니다.
that you learn best when information is presented to you in an auditory format.
즉, 정보가 청각적 형태로 제시될 때 가장 잘 배우시는 분이죠.
And if you said C, it means that you're a kinesthetic learner,
C를 선택하신 분들의 경우는 체감각에 의존한 학습자라 할 수 있습니다.
that you learn best when you get stuck in and do things with your hands.
즉, 뭐든지 제 손으로 해볼 때 가장 잘 배우시는 분이라는 걸 의미하죠.
Except, of course, as you've probably guessed,
단, 물론, 다들 짐작하고 계셨겠지만,
that it doesn't, because the whole thing is a complete myth.
이 모든 이야기 역시 잘못 알고 있는 신화에 불과합니다.
Learning styles are made up and are not supported by scientific evidence.
학습 유형이란 조작된 것이고, 이를 지원하는 과학적 증거는 없습니다.
So we know this because in tightly controlled experimental studies,
우리는 이것을 엄격하게 통제된 실험을 통해 알게 되었기 때문입니다.
when learners are given material to learn
우리가 학습자에게 학습자료를 제시할 때
either in their preferred style or an opposite style,
그들이 선호하는 유형과 정반대의 유형으로 제시했더니
it makes no difference at all to the amount of information that they retain.
학습자가 습득한 정보의 양엔 전혀 차이가 없었습니다.
And if you think about it for just a second,
그리고 잠시 생각해 보시면,
it's just obvious that this has to be true.
그게 사실이라는 게 금방 드러납니다.
It's obvious that the best presentation format
최상의 제시유형은
depends not on you, but on what you're trying to learn.
학습자에 좌우되는 것이 아니라 학습해야 할 내용에 따라 좌우됩니다.
Could you learn to drive a car, for example,
예를 들어 여러분이 운전하기를 배울 때
just by listening to someone telling you what to do
실제로 몸으로 체감하는 경험 없이
Could you solve simultaneous equations
연립 방정식을 풀어야 하는데
by talking them through in your head and without writing them down?
종이에 쓰지 않고 머리속에서 말하는 것으로 풀 수가 있을까요?
Could you revise for your architecture exams
또는 만일 여러분이 체감형식의 학습자 유형이라면, 건축학 시험을 해석적 춤을
No. What you need to do is match the material to be learned
아니죠! 배워야 할 내용을 제시된 유형에 맞추어야 합니다,
I know many of you are A-level students
여러분들 상당수가 "A"급의 우등생이라는 걸 아는데,
that will have recently gotten your GCSE results.
조만간 중등학력인증시험(GCSE) 결과를 받게 되시겠네요.
And if you didn't quite get what you were hoping for,
그런데, 만일, 여러분들이 희망했던 성적을 받지 못하게 된다 해도
then you can't really blame your learning style,
여러분들의 학습 방식을 탓해서는 안되는 겁니다.
but one thing that you might want to think about blaming is your genes.
여러분이 비난할 수 있는 한가지는 바로 유전자입니다.
So what this is all about is a recent study at University College London
이건 최근에 런던대학교(UCL)에서 수행했던 연구 결과는
found that 58 percent of the variation
여러 학생들과 그들의 중등학력인증시험 결과 사이의 차이 중 58%는
was down to genetic factors.
유전적인 요인으로 좁혀졌습니다.
That sounds like a very precise figure, so how can we tell?
매우 정밀한 수치처럼 들립니다. 그러면 어떻게 알 수 있을까요?
Well, when we want to unpack the relative contributions
유전적 요인과 환경적 요인의 상대적 기여도를 알고 싶을 때
what we can do is do a twin study.
우리가 사용할 수 있는 방식은 바로 쌍둥이 연구입니다.
So identical twins share 100 percent of their environment
일란성 쌍생아의 경우 환경적 요인과 유전적 요인 모두를
and 100 percent of their genes,
100% 똑같이 공유하게 되지만
whereas non-identical twins share 100 percent of their environment,
이란성 쌍생아의 경우는 100% 동일한 환경을 공유하지만
but just like any brother and sister, share only 50 percent of their genes.
유전자의 경우 여타의 형제자매들처럼 50% 만 공유하게 됩니다.
So by comparing how similar GCSE results are in identical twins
따라서 일란성 쌍둥이와 이란성 쌍둥이 사이의
versus non-identical twins,
인증시험 결과가 얼마나 비슷한지 비교해 보고
and doing some clever math,
여기에 약간의 수학적 계산을 더하게 되면
we can an idea of how much variation and performance is due to the environment
그 수행능력의 차이 중 어느 정도가 환경적 요인의 탓이고
and how much is due to genes.
어느 정도가 유전자 탓인지를 알 수 있게 됩니다.
And it turns out that it's about 58 percent due to genes.
이런 식으로 연구해 보니, 58% 정도가 유전자로 인한 차이였더라는 거죠.
So this isn't to undermine the hard work that you and your teachers here put in.
이것이 여러분과 선생님들이 투여한 상당한 노력을 폄하하려는 것은 아녜요.
If you didn't quite get the GCSE results that you were hoping for,
만일 여러분들이 중등학력인증시험에서 원하는 점수를 얻지 못하셨다면,
then you can always try blaming your parents, or at least their genes.
여러분들의 부모님, 적어도 그분들의 유전자 탓으로 돌려도 된다는 겁니다.
One thing that you shouldn't blame
그러나 한가지 탓해서는 안되는 것은,
is being a left-brained or right-brained learner,
'좌뇌형 인간이냐, 우뇌형 인간이냐' 하는 구분입니다.
because again, this is a myth.
왜냐하면, 이것 역시 신화이기 때문이죠.
So the myth here is that the left brain is logical,
여기에서의 신화는, 좌뇌는 논리적이어서
it's good with equations like this,
이와 같은 방정식 처리에 유리하고
and the right brain is more creative, so the right brain is better at music.
또 우뇌는 창의적이어서 음악 따위에 유리하다고 합니다.
But again, this is a myth because nearly everything that you do
다시말하지만, 이것은 신화이죠, 사실은 인간의 거의 모든 활동은
involves nearly all parts of your brain talking together,
두뇌의 모든 부분 사이의 소통이 연결되어 이루어 집니다.
even just the most mundane thing like having a normal conversation.
심지어 사소한 대화와 같은 가장 일상적인 활동조차 말이죠.
However, perhaps one reason why this myth has survived
그러나, 이런 신화가 살아남게 된 한가지 이유는
is that there is a slight grain of truth to it.
그것에 아주 소량의 진실이 들어 있기 때문입니다.
So a related version of the myth
좌뇌와 우뇌에 관한 신화 중 관련된 것은
which kind of makes sense because your brain controls the opposite hands,
일견 논리적인 게, 두뇌는 자신 반대쪽의 손을 통제하기 때문이죠.
so left-handed people,
그래서 왼손잡이 사람들은,
the right side of the brain is slightly more active
두뇌의 오른 쪽이 두뇌의 왼쪽보다 약간 더 활동적이고,
and the idea is the right-hand side is more creative.
그 아이디어는 두뇌의 오른 쪽이 더 창의적이라는 겁니다.
Now, it isn't true per se
그 이야기 자체는 사실이 아닙니다.
What is true that ambidextrous people,
사실인 건 양손잡이 사람들이 더 창의적입니다.
or people who use both hands for different tasks,
혹은 다른 작업에 양손을 모두 잘 사용하는 사람들이
are more creative thinkers than one-handed people,
이들은 한쪽 손만 사용하는 사람보다 창의적으로 생각하는 사람들입니다.
because being ambidextrous involves
양손을 능숙하게 쓰기 위해선
having both sides of the brain talk to each other a lot,
양쪽 두뇌 사이의 빈번한 소통을 관련시켜야 하기 때문에
which seems to be involved in creating flexible thinking.
유연한 사고를 만드는 것에 관련된 것처럼 보입니다.
The myth of the creative left-hander
창의적인 왼손잡이 사람에 대한 신화는
arises from the fact that being ambidextrous
양손잡이가 오른손잡이 보다는 왼손잡이 중에서
is more common amongst left-handers than right-handers,
더 흔하게 발견된다는 사실로부터 기인한 오해이며
so a grain of truth in the idea of the creative left-hander,
따라서 왼손잡이의 창의성에 관한 신화는 진실이라 인정할 만한 점이 있긴 하지만
but not much.
그렇게 상당한 부분은 아닙니다.
A related myth that you've probably heard of
이와 관련하여 여러분들께서 들어봤음직한 신화는
is that we only use 10 percent of our brains.
인간이 두뇌 중 10% 정도만 활용한다는 것입니다.
This is, again, a complete myth.
이건 다시 말해, 완전한 신화입니다.
Nearly everything that we do, even the most mundane thing,
우리가 하는 거의 모든 활동, 심지어 가장 평범한 활동조차도
uses nearly all of our brains.
우리 두뇌의 거의 모든 부분을 사용합니다.
That said, it is of course true
그렇게 말해서지만, 물론 사실인 것은,
that most of us don't use our brainpower quite as well as we could.
우리 대부분은 우리가 할 수 있는 만큼 뇌의 힘을 발휘하지 못한다는 것입니다.
So what could we do to boost our brainpower?
그러면 두뇌 활용 능력 활성화를 위해 우리가 할 수 있는 일은 뭘까요?
Maybe we could listen to a nice bit of Mozart.
어쩌면 멋진 모짜르트 음악을 들어 볼 수도 있겠죠.
Have you heard of the idea of the Mozart effect?
모짜르트 효과라는 말 들어 본적 있으신가요?
So the idea is that listening to Mozart makes you smarter
모짜르트를 들으면 더 총명해진다는 주장인데요.
and improves your performance on I.Q. tests.
아이큐 검사 결과도 향상시킨다고들 합니다.
Now again, what's interesting about this myth
이 신화에 있어서도 흥미로운 점이 또 있는데,
is that although it's basically a myth, there is a grain of truth to it.
그게 기본적으로는 신화라고 해도 일말의 진실이 담겨 있다는 사실입니다.
So the original study found that
원래의 연구에서 발견한 사실은
participants who were played Mozart music for a few minutes
참여자들 중에서 몇분 동안 모짜르트를 들은 쪽이
did better on a subsequent I.Q. test
바로 이어진 아이큐 검사 결과에서 더 나은 결과를 얻었다는 것이죠,
than participants who simply sat in silence.
그냥 조용히 앉아 있었던 참여자들과 비교해서 말이죠.
But a follow-up study recruited some people who liked Mozart music
그러나, 한 후속 연구에서 모짜르트를 좋아하는 사람들 일부와
and then another group of people
다른 쪽엔 스티븐 킹의 공포 소설의 팬들을 모집했습니다.
And they played the people the music or the stories.
그리고 음악과 공포스런 이야기를 각각 들려 주었습니다.
The people who preferred Mozart music to the stories
공포 소설보다 모짜르트 음악을 선호했던 사람들은
got a bigger I.Q. boost from the Mozart than the stories,
소설을 들었을 때보다 음악을 들은 후에 아이큐 검사 결과가 나아졌습니다.
but the people who preferred the stories to the Mozart music
그러나, 공포 소설을 모짜르트 음악보다 선호했던 피실험자들의 경우엔
got a bigger I.Q. boost from listening to the Stephen King stories
모짜르트 음악을 들었을 때보다 스티븐 킹의 소설을 듣고 난 후에
than the Mozart music.
아이큐 검사 결과가 나아졌습니다.
So the truth is that listening to something that you enjoy
그래서 진실은 여러분이 좋아하는 무엇이든지 듣는 것은
perks you up a bit and gives you a temporary I.Q. boost
두뇌가 약간 더 활성화 되면서 특정 작업에 관한 어느정도 분야에서
on a narrow range of tasks.
지능지수가 일시적으로 향상된다는 것입니다.
There's no suggestion that listening to Mozart,
연구 결과 어디서도 모짜르트를 듣거나 아님 스티븐 킹 소설을 읽으면
or indeed Stephen King stories,
장기적으로 총명해 질 것이라는 제시는 찾아볼 수 없습니다.
Another version of the Mozart myth
모짜르트 신화의 또 다른 버전으로는
is that listening to Mozart can make you not only cleverer but healthier, too.
모짜르트를 들으면 똑똑해질 뿐만 아니라 건강해지기도 한다는 것입니다.
Unfortunately, this doesn't seem to be true
이 이야기 역시 불행하게도 사실과는 거리가 멀어 보입니다
of someone who listened to the music of Mozart almost every day,
모짜르트 음악을 거의 매일 들었던 단 한 사람인,
Mozart himself,
모짜르트 자신만 봐도 말이죠.
who suffered from gonorrhea, smallpox, arthritis,
그가 평생 임질과 천연두 및 관절염으로 고생하다가,
and, what most people think eventually killed him in the end, syphilis.
많은 사람들이 믿고 있는 것처럼 결국 매독 때문에 죽었으니까요.
This suggests that Mozart should have bit more careful, perhaps,
이 사실이 제시하는 것은 모짜르트가 '성행위 상대자 고를 때 보다 더
when choosing his sexual partners.
신중했어야 했다' 는 것입니다.
But how do we choose a partner?
그렇다면 우리는 어떤 식으로 성행위 상대자를 골라야 할까요?
So a myth that I have to say is sometimes spread a bit by sociologists
이와 관련된 신화는 일정 부분 사회학자들이 퍼뜨리고 있는 것인데,
is that our preferences in a romantic partner are a product of our culture,
낭만적 이성을 선호하는 것은 모두 문화적 산물이라는 신화입니다.
that they're very culturally specific.
즉 그것들은 문화적으로 특정화되어 있다는 것인데요.
But in fact, the data don't back this up.
그러나 사실, 데이터는 이러한 주장을 뒷받침해 주지 않습니다.
A famous study surveyed people from [37] different cultures across the globe,
전세계 37개국의 다를 문화권에서 여론조사를 한 유명한 연구인데,
from Americans to Zulus,
미국인들로부터 줄루족까지 포함한 것입니다.
on what they look for in a partner.
주제는 파트너에게서 그들이 중점적으로 보는 것은 무엇인가? 였죠.
And in every single culture across the globe,
그리고 전 세계의 모든 문화권에서 공히
men placed more value on physical attractiveness in a partner
남자들은 여성들보다 상대자의 신체적 매력에 더 큰 비중을 두었고,
and in every single culture, too,
모든 문화권에서 공히
women placed more importance than did men on ambition and high earning power.
여성들은 남성들에 비해 상대의 야망이나 수입능력에 더 큰 비중을 두었습니다.
In every culture, too,
또한, 모든 문화권에서
men preferred women who were younger than themselves,
남자들은 자신보다 나이가 어린 여성을 선호했습니다.
an average of, I think it was 2.66 years,
평군적으로 대개 2.66세 정도 차이로 말입니다.
and in every culture, too,
또한, 모든 문화권에서
women preferred men who were older than them,
여성들은 자신보다 나이가 많은 남성을 선호했습니다.
so an average of 3.42 years,
평균 3.42세 차이로 말입니다.
which is why we've got here "Everybody needs a Sugar Daddy."
그래서 이런 말이 나왔나 보죠? "모든 사람은 물주가 필요해!"
So moving on from trying to score with a partner
이제 이성 관계에서 득점하려는 화제로부터
to trying to score in basketball or football or whatever your sport is.
농구나 축구 같은 스포츠에서 득점하려는 쪽으로 옮겨 보도록 하죠.
The myth here is that sportsmen go through hot-hand streaks, Americans call them,
이 신화는 운동선수들이 미국인들이, '핫-핸드 스트릭스'라고 부르고
or purple patches, we sometimes say in England,
영국에서는 우리가 가끔 '퍼플 패치스'라고 부르는데요,
where they just can't miss, like this guy here.
두 표현 모두 여기 이 선수처럼 '공을 계속 넣는다'는 의미죠.
But in fact, what happens is that if you analyze the pattern
그러나 사실, 득점하고 실점하는 실제 패턴을
of hits and misses statistically,
통계적으로 분석해 보면
it turns out that it's nearly always at random.
거의 항상 무작위적인 결과인 것으로 판명됩니다.
Your brain creates patterns from the randomness.
여러분의 두뇌는 무질서 속에서 패턴을 만듭니다.
If you toss a coin,
동전을 계속 던지면,
a streak of heads or tails is going to come out somewhere in the randomness,
무작위적인 시행값 어디에선가 앞면, 또는 뒷면이 연이어 나올 것입니다.
and because the brain likes to see patterns where there are none,
그르고 두뇌는 패턴이 없는 곳에서도 보는 것을 즐기기 때문에
we look at these streaks and attribute meanings to them
이처럼 연속적인 상황을 보게되면 거기에 의미를 부여하게 되고,
and say, "Yeah he's really on form today,"
"오늘 저 선수 정말 재량을 다 발휘하는데" 라고 말하는 겁니다.
whereas actually you would get the same pattern
반면에 실제로는 여러분도 똑같은 패턴을 얻을 수 있습니다
if you were just getting hits and misses at random.
무작위로 골을 넣다가, 놓치다 하는 것을 반복하면 말입니다.
So an exception to this, however, is penalty shootouts.
그러나, 물론, 이에 대한 예외적인 상황은 바로 페널티킥 상황입니다.
A recent study looking at penalty shootouts in football
미식축구 경기의 페널티킥 사례에 관한 최근 한 연구에 따르면
shows that players who represent countries
페널티 킥에 나선 선수가
with a very bad record in penalty shootouts,
페널티킥 기록이 저조한 국가의 대표 선수일수록
like, for example, England,
가령, 영국 같은 나라의 선수는
tend to be quicker to take their shots than countries with a better record,
기록이 좋은 나라 선수들에 비해 더 급하게 공을 찬다고 합니다.
and presumably as a result, they're more likely to miss.
결과적으로 골을 놓칠 가능성이 커지는 것으로 가정할 수 있는데,
Which raises the question
그 가정으로 제기되는 문제는,
of if there's any way that we could improve people's performance.
사람들의 수행능력를 향상시킬 수 있는 방법이 과연 존재하는 걸까?
And one thing you might think about doing
할 수 있는 일에 대해 생각해 볼 수 있는 한가지는
is punishing people for their misses and seeing if that improves them.
실수에 대해 처벌하는 것이 수행능력을 향상시키는지 관찰하는 방법이 있는데요,
This idea, the effect that punishment can improve performance,
처벌이 수행능력을 향상시키는 데 영향을 준다는 이러한 아이디어는,
is what participants thought they were testing
여러분이 심리학과 학생들이라면 들어봤을 법한
in Milgram's famous learning and punishment experiment
밀그램의 유명한 '학습과 처벌' 실험에 참여한 피실험자들이
that you've probably heard about if you're a psychology student.
검증하게 될 거라 믿었던 개념이었습니다.
The story goes that participants were prepared to give
그 이야기에 따르면 참여자들이 잘못된 대답을 할 경우
what they believed to be fatal electric shocks to a fellow participant
동료 참여자에게 치명적인 전기충격이라고 서로 믿고 있던
when they got a question wrong,
벌을 주는것으로 준비하고 있었어요.
just because someone in a white coat told them to.
단지 하얀 코트를 입고 있는 사람이 그렇게 하라고 시켰기 때문에 말이죠.
But this story is a myth for three reasons.
그러나 이 이야기는 세가지 이유로 인해 신화입니다.
Firstly and most crucially, the lab coat wasn't white, it was in fact grey.
첫째, 가장 중요한 건 실험실 가운은 흰색이 아니라 회색이었다라는 점이죠.
Secondly, the participants were told before the study
둘째, 참여자들은 실험하기 전에와
and reminded any time they raised a concern,
참여자들이 걱정을 표현할 때마다 상기시키는 말을 들었는데,
that although the shocks were painful, they were not fatal
전기 충격이 고통스럽기는 하지만, 치명적이지는 않으며
and indeed caused no permanent damage whatsoever.
실제로 영구적인 손상을 남기는 일은 없을 거라는 것이었습니다.
And thirdly, participants didn't give the shocks
셋째, 참여자들은 단지 가운을 입은 사람이 시켜 전기충격을 주지는 않았죠.
When they were interviewed after the study,
실험이 끝나고 그들의 인터뷰를 했을 때
all the participants said that they firmly believed
모든 참여자들은 강한 신념을 밝혔는데,
that the learning and punishment study served a worthy scientific purpose
'학습과 처벌' 연구가 과학적으로 가치있는 목적을 수행했기 때문에
which would have enduring gains for science
비록 동료 참여자들에게 가해진 순간적인 불편함에 반해서
Okay, so I've been talking for about 12 minutes now,
그러다 보니 제가 이야기를 한 지 벌써 12분이 되었습니다.
and you've probably been sitting there listening to me,
여러분들 중에는 아마 거기 앉아서 제 이야기를 들으시는 동안
analyzing my speech patterns and body language
저의 말투와 몸짓을 분석하면서
and trying to work out if you should take any notice of what I'm saying,
제가 말하는 어떤 것을 인지해야 할까 해결하려고 하셨을 겁니다,
because although we all think we can catch a liar
왜냐하면 우리 모두가 사람이 말하는 패턴과 몸짓으로도
from their body language and speech patterns,
거짓말 여부를 알아내는 것이 가능하다고 생각하지만,
hundreds of psychological tests over the years have shown
오랜 세월 수백 회에 걸쳐 행해진 실제 심리검사의 결과를 보면
that all of us, including police officers and detectives,
우리들 모두는, 심지어 경찰관이나 탐정들을 포함해서도
are basically at chance when it comes to detecting lies from body language
기본적으로 몸짓과 언어적 패턴으로 거짓말을 탐지하는 것은
and verbal patterns.
운에 맞길 수 밖에는 없는 것입니다.
Interestingly, there is one exception:
흥미롭게도 한 가지 예외가 있는데요:
TV appeals for missing relatives.
실종된 친척을 찾아 달라고 호소하는 TV 홍보입니다.
It's quite easy to predict when the relatives are missing
친척이 실종된 시기와 TV에 나와 호소하는 사람이
and when the appealers have in fact murdered the relatives themselves.
실종된 친척을 스스로 살해했을 경우를 예측하기란 상당히 쉽습니다.
So hoax appealers are more likely to shake their heads, to look away,
거짓으로 호소하는 사람들은 고개를 흔들거나, 시선을 회피하고
and to make errors in their speech,
말 실수를 할 확률이 커지는 반면
whereas genuine appealers are more likely
진심으로 호소하는 사람들은 경우
to express hope that the person will return safely
실종자가 안전하게 돌아오길 바라는 심정을 표현하고
and to avoid brutal language.
잔인한 말을 피해서 표현하는 경향이 커집니다.
So, for example, they might say "taken from us" rather than "killed."
예를 들어, "죽였다"라는 표현 대신, "우리에게서 뺏아간"같은 표현을 쓰죠.
Speaking of which, it's about time I killed this talk,
그렇게 말하다 보니, 제 강연을 죽여야 할 때가 되었습니다,
but before I do, I just want to give you in 30 seconds
그렇게 하기 전에, 저는 여러분에게 지금부터 30초 동안
the overarching myth of psychology.
심리학 전반에 걸쳐 있는 신화 하나를 말씀드리겠습니다.
So the myth is that psychology is just a collection of interesting theories,
이는 심리학이란 단지 흥미로운 이론을 모아 놓은 것에 불과하고
all of which say something useful and all of which have something to offer.
그 이론 모두가 유용한 뭔가를 말해주고 제공할 만한 것을 갖고 있다는 신화죠.
What I hope to have shown you in the past few minutes
지난 몇분 동안에 보여드린 것으로 제가 희망하는 바는
is that this isn't true.
그게 사실이 아니라는 것입니다.
What we need to do is assess psychological theories
우리가 반드시 해야 할 일은 심리학적 이론을 평가하는 것입니다.
by seeing what predictions they make,
어떤 예측을 하는 지 보는 것으로,
whether that is that listening to Mozart makes you smarter,
그게 모짜르트를 들으면 똑똑해진다는 주장이건,
that you learn better when information is presented in your preferred learning style
학습자가 선호하는 학습 유형으로 정보가 제시되면 더 잘 배운다는 주장이건
or whatever it is, all of these are testable empirical predictions,
또는 어떤 주장이든, 이런 모든 가설은 경험적 예측으로 검증할 수 있고
and the only way we can make progress
심리학이 발전할 수 있는 유일한 길은
is to test these predictions against the data
이러한 모든 예측들을 실제 데이터로 검증하는 것입니다.
in tightly controlled experimental studies.
엄격하게 통제된 실험적 연구를 통해서 말입니다.
And it's only by doing so that we can hope to discover
그렇게 하는 것만이 우리가 발견할 수 있을 거라고 희망할 수 있는 겁니다.
which of these theories are well supported,
이러한 이론들 중에 어떤 것이 근거를 제대로 갖춘 것이고,
and which, like all the ones I've told you about today, are myths.
어떤 것이 오는 제가 말씀드린 것처럼 신화에 불과한 것들인지를 말입니다.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
(Applause)
(박수)